<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right notion of honour as it was delivered in a sermon before the King at Newmarket, Octob. 4, 1674. Published by His Majesties special command. : With annotations, the contents whereof are in the following leaf / by Nath. Vincent, D.D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majesty, and Fellow of Clare-Hall in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12083585</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12083585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 587:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right notion of honour as it was delivered in a sermon before the King at Newmarket, Octob. 4, 1674. Published by His Majesties special command. : With annotations, the contents whereof are in the following leaf / by Nath. Vincent, D.D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majesty, and Fellow of Clare-Hall in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 pts. ([4], 27; 52 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell at the Rose and Crown in S. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 52.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Annotations appear on pages 1 and 2 of second pagination. "A general address to all bountiful encouragers of religion and learning, ... in Cambridge:" pages 3-7.</note>
                  <note>Formerly Wing V419 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>University of Cambridge.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms VIII, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53659:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53659:1"/>
            <p> THE RIGHT NOTION OF HONOUR: As it was delivered in a SERMON BEFORE THE KING. At NEWMARKET, <hi>Octob.</hi> 4. 1674. <hi>Publiſhed by his Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi> WITH ANNOTATIONS: The Contents whereof are in the following Leaf. By <hi>NATH. VINCENT,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to His Majeſty, and Fellow of <hi>Clare-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCLXXXV.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53659:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:53659:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Annotations.</head>
            <p>THE occaſion of publiſhing this Diſcourſe, after its ſuppreſſion for ſo many years.</p>
            <p>A ſure Expedient for attaining the greateſt Honour.</p>
            <p>This conception proved agreeable to the Divine Oeconomy, in ſeveral Particulars.</p>
            <p>An account of the excellent Life, and a Specimen of the admirable Morals, of that old <hi>Chineſe</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher <hi>Cumfuſu.</hi> Wherein we find the happy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Natural, and the Improved ſenſe of Honour, upon the Manners of that People, and the Proſperity of their Empire, in antient times.</p>
            <p>The contrary Sentiments of Ambitious, Revengeful or Miſtaken Men, repreſented in Hiſtorical Parallels between the old Politick Frights of Tyranny and Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very in other Countries, and the like ſeditious Clamours among our ſelves in the late Rebellion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:53659:3"/>
            <q>
               <p>HOneſtatem voco intelligibilem pulchritudinem. <bibl>S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </bibl> Honeſtum idem quod decorum ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuale. <bibl>
                     <hi>Dionyſ. de Div. Nomin.</hi>
                  </bibl> Formam ipſam &amp; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam faciem honeſti vides, quae ſi oculis cerneretur, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiles amores, ut ait Plato, excitaret ſapientiae. <bibl>
                     <hi>Cic.</hi>
                  </bibl> Caeſar cum quoſdam ornare voluit, non ipſos honeſtavit, ſed ornamenta ipſa turpavit. <bibl>
                     <hi>Idem.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<bibl> 
                     <hi>Hierocl.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>See the laſt Particular of the Sermon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53659:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. VIII. part of Verſe v.</bibl> —And haſt crowned Him with Glory and Honour.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THOUGH there is not any thing in the World, that hath been always more valued and deſired than Honour, yet there is nothing that has been ſo little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and explicated. True Honour does anſwer the Eſteem that hath been always ſet upon it. It is the beſt of our attainments in this Life: Nay, it is all we can return to God himſelf, for all the Bleſſings he heaps upon us. Next under God, our greateſt Obligations are to our Prince, and to our Parents: Now the Honour we pay to the Fathers of our Country, for the ſecurity of our Perſons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53659:4"/> and Fortunes, and to thoſe that bred us for our Nurture and Education, is the fulleſt Account of our Duty to both. Our Labours, Hardſhips, and Dangers; the ſharpeſt Pains, the cruelleſt Tortures, the worſt of Deaths we can undergo, have no greater temporal Reward than Honour. When God Almighty would make a Creature, as happy as any thing could be, lower than an Angel, he created <hi>Adam:</hi> of whom the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſays, <hi>That his Maker gave him Dominion over the Works of his Hands, and put all things in ſubjection under his Feet.</hi> In ſhort, He made him a King, and crowned him upon his Birth-day, he crowned him with Glory and Honour.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in this place deſcribing the infinite Goodneſs of God, in creating Man after his own Image, and in repairing afterwards that Image in him, calls His original Righteouſneſs, and the Supplies of Grace after the Fall, his Honour. For as we call the Perfections of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, to which we owe our Beeing and Happineſs, the Honour of God; ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53659:4"/> the Integrity and the Renovation of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, are the Honour of Man, becauſe they make him capable of doing good. An Honour ſo great, that to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it fully, the Original reads the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parts of the Verſe thus, <hi>Thou haſt made him little lower</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>than God, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a God.</hi> Now as we call the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Perfections of God, and the Moral or Religious Excellencies of Man, their Honour, upon account of the Benefits conferred by God upon Man, and by good Men upon their fellow Creatures, ſo is it likewiſe in the caſe of Temporal, Secondary, Imperfect Honour. Humane Authority, Power and Greatneſs is called Honour, becauſe it ſeems to imply and ſuppoſe in the Poſſeſſors, thoſe Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which tend to the Uſe, Benefit, and Welfare of Mankind. Thus Magiſtrates, even when they are corrupt, are honoured, becauſe by their Station and Condition, they are in many reſpects uſeful, and have always more Power and better Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of doing good than inferiour Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: From whoſe better Reſolutions,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53659:5"/> for the time to come, we cannot expect ſo much of publick Benefit. For this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when Noblemen are diſſolute, our Parents vicious, the Aged profligate, there is ſtill ſomething of Reſpect, and Honour due to them, though the Proportion of it is ſtrangely leſſened, by their defects and miſcarriages. That which I have here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, is to give an account of Honour, both in its beſt Senſe, and in its largeſt Extent. To which purpoſe I conclude, That Honour is the greateſt Excellency both of uncreated and finite Nature, that we form our Apprehenſions of any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency according to its Title to Eſteem, and that we have the higheſt and moſt juſt Eſteem of thoſe Perfections by which we are moſt of all relieved, ſupplied, aſſiſted and comforted. What I have been hitherto deſcribing, I thus define; <hi>True Honour is eminent and beneficial Goodneſs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted:</hi> And in the common imperfect No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, <hi>It is any degree, capacity, or reſemblance of ſignalized Worth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53659:5"/>
            <p> This Definition, as it comprehends the Particulars of my following Diſcourſe, ſo it ſerves us to make a Judgment of thoſe two Conceptions of Honour, which are as diſtant in their Senſe, as their Age in the World. The one is old, the other very new: the former is from <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> and their Followers; the latter from the <hi>Leviathan</hi> and his Diſciples. According to the old Notion, it is nothing but a Mark or Inſcription upon ſuppoſed Goodneſs: According to the new one, It is only an Inſtance, or Argument of Power. <hi>Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> ſays the <hi>Leviathan, is whatſoever Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Action or Quality, is an Argument and Sign of Power.</hi> His Comment is as bad as his Text, for he goes on thus. <hi>Covetouſneſs of great Riches, and Ambition of great Honours, are Honourable; as ſigns of Power to obtain them. Nor does it alter the caſe of Honour, whether an Action (ſo it be great and difficult, and conſequently a ſign of much Power) be juſt or unjuſt: For Honour conſiſteth only in the Opinion of Power.</hi> For proof of this, he mentions the fabulous Rapes and Thefts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53659:6"/> of the Heathen Gods, and he ſays, <hi>That till there were conſtituted great Commonwealths, it was thought no diſhonour to be a Pirate, or a Highway-Thief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now he that makes Power to be the Foundation of Right, muſt make Honour to be the effect of Power, though never ſo ill gotten. When an Uſurper is to be upheld and defended; Injuſtice, Violence, Ambition, Cruelty, Theft, Murder, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege and Oppreſſion, muſt be of his Life-guard. I muſt needs ſay, That although the old Opinion of Honour is defective, it is far more tolerable than this Novel and lewd Extravagancy.</p>
            <p>Would we then know what is to be underſtood by true and ſolid Honour, we muſt be inſtructed by the Principles of Religion, and not the bare Dictates of Natural Reaſon; we muſt learn it from the School of Chriſt, and not of <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> or any other, and worſe Philoſopher. So that the Heads of my following Diſcourſe will be theſe two Particulars.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53659:6"/>
            <p n="1">I. According to the Opinion moſt Men have of Honour, it is either nothing at all, or a very ſlight; empty, imaginary buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Chriſtian Inſtitution does give us the only true account of Honour, and doth advance us to the higheſt degrees of it.</p>
            <p n="1">I. For the firſt Particular, It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that Honour is a greater reality than moſt People make it. It muſt be ſomething more than what it is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to be by the Leviathan-Philoſophy, if there be any ſuch thing in Nature. For Power alone, and as it is diſtinguiſhed from Goodneſs, is no ſign or inſtance of Honour.</p>
            <p>Power oppoſed to Goodneſs is no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or Excellency. If Greatneſs were nothing more than the Commiſſion of great Robberies at Land, or Piracies at Sea, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of great Honours, the Covetouſneſs of great Riches, the Gratification of Envy, Malice, Revenge and Cruelty; the worſt of Creatures would be the moſt Honourable, and the Prince of Darkneſs would be the greateſt Prince in Nature.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53659:7"/>
            <p> Power, when it is injurious and hurtful, when it is employed in the Oppreſſion of thoſe it ſhould preſerve, is no real excellency. To deſtroy and ruine is the baſeſt and moſt degenerate Action that the worſt of Men, and even the Devil himſelf can be guilty of.</p>
            <p>The Beeing and Welfare of Mankind are the Reaſons of that Honour we pay unto the Author and the Inſtruments thereof. But if to deſtroy and oppreſs is unworthy and misbecoming a generous Mind; the Power ſo to do, abſtractly conſidered, can never be Honourable; nor plead a Title to the Significations of that kind Eſteem and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Opinion in which external Honour does conſiſt.</p>
            <p>So that Honour is juſt the contrary to what the <hi>Leviathan</hi> would make it. It muſt he ſomething elſe than what he calls by that Name, or there is no ſuch thing in Nature. And indeed, as it is better deſcribed by the Schoolmen, and their Maſters the old Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, we can never make any thing of it, that we can call ſubſtantial and ſolid.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53659:7"/>
            <p> As I do not give the name of real Honour to any Excellency that is only the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Reaſon of it, ſo neither can I grant that Appellation to the Externals of it, to that reſpect and deference which is often paid, where it is not at all due. I call Honour <hi>atteſted Goodneſs,</hi> ſince in the beſt common account of it, it is only <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. Rhet. l. 1. c. 5.</note> a ſign or proof that others think well of us; and ſo Honour ſhall be ſometimes given, not for the ſake of any good Actions, but only of a Power or Obligation to perform them.</p>
            <p>It is commonly ſaid to have its being in thoſe that pay it, and not in thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. It is ſomething, belike, we call ours, which we can neither command nor ſecure; our own undoubted Right, that is always poſſeſſed and diſpoſed of by other People.</p>
            <p>According to theſe Men, it is only a ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Slavery, or a Maſs of uncertain Riches; a dangerous Truſt, or a barren Title; a Formality, a Shew, a Ceremony, an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription; the late reward of macerating Study, or of the cruel hardſhips of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53659:8"/> Camp; the eaſie Spoil of Flattery, Malice, Ambition or Avarice; not ſo often conferred upon known Merit, as revoked upon Miſtake or Prejudice: the mark of the Envious, and the frequent purchace of the Undeſerving; though long expected, and gained with La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, Care, and Toil, yet quickly forfeited by Negligence, Paſſion, Miſchance, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Now Honour, which is the moſt valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enjoyment in this World, and which, in its Perfection, is the Bleſſedneſs of the World to come; that which is the greateſt Gift we can receive from God or Man, muſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amount to ſomething more than we can find in the foregoing Deſcription of it. Which brings me to the ſecond Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Chriſtian Inſtitution doth give us the only true account of Honour, and does advance us to the higheſt Degrees of it. It ſhows us what Honour is in God, and in Man.</p>
            <p n="1">I. We are inſtructed by the heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of our Religion, in the Nature and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53659:8"/> Reaſons of that Honour we render unto God. It is obſerved, that the Greatneſs of earthly Potentates concerns only their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Allies, thoſe they protect or aſſiſt, and is not regarded by the Inhabitants of far diſtant Countries.</p>
            <p>Honour is never paid as a juſt Debt, but to thoſe Excellencies by which Mankind is ſome way or other bettered, profited, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared. The Excellencies of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do then only affect and raviſh us, when we conſider that we owe our Happineſs, Preſervation, and Beeing, to them. We therefore adore and reverence the Divine Goodneſs, Bounty, and Mercy, becauſe we are thereby not only redeemed from infinite Miſery, but ſurrounded with innumerable Bleſſings.</p>
            <p>God Almighty never appeared with ſo much Glory in the World, as when in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Perſon of the Trinity, he condeſcended for the recovery of Mankind, to take our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon him, and to humble himſelf even unto the Death of the Croſs.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53659:9"/>
            <p> When the Son of God came down from Heaven, the way he took to illuſtrate his Glory, was by doing the greateſt Good, and by making Peace between God and Man. When he was to prove his Divinity, he wrought not one Miracle, only to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and aſtoniſh the Beholders, not one that did not ſhow he was ſent to bring Health and Salvation to the Sons of Men, and to be the great Example, and effectual Promoter, of Goodneſs and Piety.</p>
            <p>This was the end of the Creation, for this reaſon did <hi>the Heavens declare the Glory of God, and the Firmament ſhew his Handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work,</hi> that the manifeſtation of his Goodneſs might be the Glory of his Power.</p>
            <p>He framed the World by his omnipotent Hand, not that his Creatures ſhould for ever ſtand gazing, wondring and amuſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at his Power, but that they ſhould be led on by the conſideration of it to admire his Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>He is unchangeable in his Nature, and cannot receive any Additions to his Glory
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53659:9"/> and Happineſs, by all our Praiſes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. This therefore was his Motive, That it was a proper Work, an action hugely befitting, ſuitable and congruous to infinite Goodneſs, to communicate, diſcover and manifeſt it ſelf, in the exerciſe of that immenſe Wiſdom and Power with which it is joyned.</p>
            <p>Finite Beeings were not created upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of any Uſe, Benefit, or new Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to their Maker, who was entirely happy from all Eternity, in the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelf, and the infinite Raviſhments of his inexpreſſibly-glorious Nature. But he ſpoke us into Beeing, and exerciſed his Almighty Power in the Production of all things, becauſe it was the moſt natural Uſe of inexhauſtible Goodneſs, to diffuſe, open and exert it ſelf in all the Varieties of the greateſt Love, and the wiſeſt Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance: To the end he might behold in every Region, through the vaſt Tracts of Nature, ten thouſand times ten thouſand Myriads of Repreſentations, and clear Images of his boundleſs Goodneſs: That he might not only be entertained at the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53659:10"/> dawning of the World, with thoſe firſt Anthems in the Celebration of his glorious Bounty by the Sons of the Morning, and with the Adorations, Praiſes and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings of his Church throughout all Ages of the World; but likewiſe by all the bright Legions of Angels, by all the Companions of the glorified Order, by the whole Quire of Heaven, enthroned Martyrs, rejoycing Sufferers, triumphant Captives, crowned Saints, comforted Mourners, and the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect; aſcribing <note place="margin">Rev. 4. 11. c. 5. 13. c. 19. 1.</note> Honour, Salvation, Bleſſing, Glory and Power unto our God for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee that Honour in God, ſo far as it commands the due regard of intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Beeings, is the Manifeſtation of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs in our Temporal or Eternal Happineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſtianity alone does rightly inform us, what Honour is in Man: Namely, that it is both the reward and the diſcharge of his Duty.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Honour in Man is the reward of his Duty, either in this World, or in the next. It is here, the Benefit that accrues to us from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53659:10"/> the good Opinion of wiſe and good Men; it is what we gain by our Moral or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Excellencies, by our Services in the Church or in the State; in the Court or in the Camp; by our Tongues or Hands; by our Pens or Swords.</p>
            <p>It is the Princes Favour, the ſence of good Laws, the munificence of Founders and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors, in the encouragement of that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Induſtry to which the corrupted Nature of Man is of all things the moſt averſe.</p>
            <p>In reference to the other World, Honour is that Goodneſs which does entitle us to the Divine Favour and Acceptance; whereby we are admitted into the neareſt Relation unto himſelf; by which good Men become his adopted Children, a choſen Generation, a royal Prieſthood, not Servants only, which is Honour enough, but the Sons of the moſt High, and more than that, Kings and Prieſts unto God: Hereby they receive the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance as well as the Adoption of Sons, and the Kingdom prepared for them, from the beginning of the World; immortal Honour, and an exceeding weight of Glory.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53659:11"/>
            <p n="2">(2.) Honour is not only the Reward, but it is likewiſe the diſcharge and exemplary Performance of our Duty. Honour, (quite contrary to what the <hi>Leviathan</hi> aſſerts) is that quality or action which is a ſign of extraordinary Goodneſs. To turn his Words, I aſſert the contempt of great Riches, and the refuſal of great Honours to be Honourable, as they are Signs of that unuſual Goodneſs which does at the ſame time both deſerve and deſpiſe them.</p>
            <p>The Hebrew words for Glory and Honour <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifie a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable quality and endowment, as well as Promotion or Ornament. The latter without the former is the leaſt part of Nobility; which is then compleat and perfect, when Power and Goodneſs meet together.</p>
            <p>We therefore find in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 17.</note> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> That there is a greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence due to our Superiors, than what their mere Power and Authority requires of us; That the Elders who rule well are to be counted worthy of double Honour.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53659:11"/> In the ſight of God, and the opinion of all good Men, Perſons of Honour are far leſs noble by their Birth, and the higheſt Extraction, than by Virtue and humble Piety.</p>
            <p>Upon this account it is; that in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Patriarchs, <hi>Japhet</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Noah,</hi> is thruſt down beneath his two younger Brothers, and <hi>Sem</hi> the ſecond Son is named and reputed as the Eldeſt. For this reaſon <hi>Abraham</hi> was named before <hi>Haran</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Terah, Iſaac</hi> was ſet before <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> advanced above his elder Brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> Hence it was, that <hi>Jacob,</hi> in Bleſſing his Sons, laid his right Hand upon <hi>Ephraim</hi>'s Head, who was the Younger, and his left upon <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> the firſt-born.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> bequeathed to the Schools the common received Notion of Honour, he taught the World to believe that Honour has its being <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eth. Nicom. c.</note> rather in thoſe that yield it, than in the Perſons honoured. When he maintained this, he had a regard only to the Ceremonies, the attire and externals of Honour, not to the Foundation and Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53659:12"/> the Reaſons and genuine Cauſes of it. For he adds at the ſame time <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eth. Nicon. c. 3.</note>, that People ſeem to purſue Honour in hopes to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good Men.</p>
            <p>He ſays, that <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in all thoſe things or actions which are juſtly rewarded with Honour, there is Honeſty and Virtue. This he delivers as a plain Demonſtration, and makes it <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rhet. l. 1. c. 9</note> a neceſſary Conſequence, for Virtue to be honourable. He ſhews us with great acuteneſs, the nature and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of Honour and Virtue, when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines the former to be <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 1. c. 5.</note> the proof of an opinion in others, which is a benefit to our ſelves, and the latter to be that <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 1. c. 9.</note> Power in us whereby we are beneficial unto others. They are <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 1. c. 5.</note> honoured (ſays he) in Juſtice, and in the higheſt degree, that do good in the World: But yet ſtill the Man is honoured that has the Power of doing Good.</p>
            <p>Theſe Sentiments of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> have paſſed for ſound Divinity among the Scholaſtick Doctors: who tell us, That bad Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and vicious Parents are to be honoured, as they have the Stamp, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53659:12"/> or Authority of Almighty God: That Nobility and Age are honourable, meerly as Signs or Reſemblances of that Vertue, which is the eternal Reaſon of Honour.</p>
            <p>So that when the forementioned Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications are wanting, then it is that Men give Honour where Honour is not due, then are they guilty of the old Idolatry of throwing Stones to <hi>Mercury</hi>'s Heap, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by <hi>(b) Solomon;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s reſpect <note place="margin">(h) Prov. 25.</note> of Perſons.</p>
            <p>This we are taught even by Nature it ſelf; for all Mankind hath naturally ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Nation, as well as of the Senſe and Deſire of Honour. There is an old Pagan Empire on the further ſide of <hi>Aſia,</hi> where the Religion and Learning, which they had for above two thouſand years, was to ſtudy the repair of Humane Nature, the perfection of Government, and the Reaſons of Honour. Their Emperor (whom they ſtiled the Son of Heaven) was for the moſt part a Philoſopher, and always a very improved Perſon. Their Nobility was not from Families, but from Wiſdom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53659:13"/> and Knowledge: And as Men grew emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for their Intellectual and Moral En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, ſo they were accordingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched and preferred.</p>
            <p>There are Inſtances enough from whence we may conclude, that by attending to the ſound Dictates of Reaſon, we may raiſe our ſelves to greater Honour, than by any other Methods, beſides Chriſtian Piety, and the moſt ennobling Precepts of our Religion. Which is the laſt Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>2. As the Doctrine of our Saviour gives us the trueſt Account of Honour, ſo its due Practice does advance us to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degrees of it. As our natural Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Juſtice, Honeſty, and Goodneſs, were our firſt embelliſhment, ſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery and improvement of them, by the Grace of the Goſpel, is the higheſt degree of Honour that mortal Man can arrive at.</p>
            <p>That which is the greateſt Perfection, is likewiſe the greateſt Ornament of Humane Nature.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53659:13"/>
            <p> Upon this account it was, that <note n="(a)" place="margin">Plato <hi>in Alcib. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv. Phadr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, among the Greeks, and <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Frigidus &amp; Sylvis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilo decuſſit honorem.</hi> Virg. Georg. 2. <hi>Hunc virum bonum dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſti, &amp; hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris cauſa ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellaſti</hi> Cic. pro Q. R.</note> 
               <hi>Honor</hi> with the Latins were uſed to ſignifie both Honeſty and Beauty. For as the clearneſs of the Complexion, and the proportion of Parts, is the Beauty of the Body; ſo the Purity of the Mind, and the Harmony, or correſpondence of our Actions to the Principles of Reaſon and Religion, is not only the Beauty, and charming ſweetneſs of the Soul, but an Honour like that which we pay unto God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Such is the Beauty of Holineſs, ſo love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are the Features of Goodneſs, that it is admired by all the World, and the very worſt of men; like the innocence of its Divine Author, to which <hi>Pilate</hi> bore wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when he ſacrificed it to the malice of the Jews.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, there is nothing ſo foul, mis-ſhapen, and ugly as Sin, there is no Monſter ſo deformed, no Beaſt ſo filthy; could we ſee it in all its lineaments, we ſhould find it more hideous than the Devil himſelf in his worſt ſhape; it is far
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53659:14"/> more black than it was ever yet paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>But now the everlaſting Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Goſpel does ennoble and raiſe us as many Degrees above Nature, as the attainments of Nature and Reaſon all one can advance us above the level of Beaſts.</p>
            <p>By the conduct of Reaſon we are brought to the Honour of being tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, liberal, juſt, merciful, kind, and faithful: But by our Chriſtian Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the guidance of the Spirit of Grace, it is our Glory, and Crown of rejoycing, that we do not only abſtain from the filthineſs of the Fleſh, but the uncleanneſs of the Spirit; that we are ſo far from invading what is our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that we do not ſo much as look upon it with a covetous, or impure Eye: That we can be kind where we expect no return, and love others beſides our Friends, and pity thoſe Enemies which other Men hate.</p>
            <p>When Sin had filled the World with Contention, Fierceneſs, and Cruelty;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53659:14"/> when the Teeth of the old Serpent that were ſown in the accurſed Earth, had ſprung up in a Race of Men that were all in Arms againſt one another; how glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious was that Chriſtian Charity that could forgive an Injury, do good to an Enemy, pray for a Perſecutor, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve an impoveriſh'd Oppreſſor!</p>
            <p>Surely there is no Honour in this World ſo great as to deſire, contrive and promote the Welfare of all Mankind: to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned like the Providence of God, for the good of the whole Creation.</p>
            <p>That Chriſtian Charity which thinketh no evil, is more glorious, as well as more laſting, than all the greatneſs of this World: Nay, the Glory which ſhall be revealed hereafter, is not worthy to be compared unto it, for that will but make us like unto the Angels, this will make us like unto God.</p>
            <p>Such Honour have all good men in the moſt private Capacity, which one would think ſufficient to ſatisfie any pardonable Ambition, and yet it is not to be named with the Glory of Pious Greatneſs.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53659:15"/>
            <p> The Virtues of Princes and Grandees, are the greateſt Temporal Bleſſings to Mankind. Our Saviour ſpeaking of the Kings of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſays, they were ſtiled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Benefactors. Such, they always are, or ought to be.</p>
            <p>They that govern ſhould be eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bountiful and Pious. The World had been a foul reproach to him that made it, if when he erected the Government of it, he had not given Power, Credit, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority to Goodneſs, and debaſed wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs by the diſtinct Characters of ſhame and hatred.</p>
            <p>Had the Almighty committed the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World to the monſtrous <hi>Leviathan;</hi> had Violence been the Rule and Standard of humane Affairs; had Cruelty been allowable, and Rapine juſt, the World had quickly been tumbled into the Confuſions of its firſt Chaos.</p>
            <p>It is the Glory of good Princes and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, that they are the Inſtruments of the Divine Providence in preſerving Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from thoſe Deſolations, into which their wild Paſſions would certainly plunge them.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53659:15"/>
            <p> That the World might ſubſiſt, when Sin had diſcompoſed it, God was pleaſed to ordain and ſeparate ſome particular Men for the conduct and protection of the reſt: to be more his Image, than others of the ſame Race: to repreſent him after a more lively manner in that Goodneſs to which we owe our Beeing and Preſervation; and withal to derive and convey it unto thoſe, who continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally depend upon it.</p>
            <p>The World is upheld, and the order of things maintained by the Charity and good Offices of good Men to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: not of all good Men alike, but of thoſe more eſpecially, who were born for that very end of a better Race, and were ſent into the World better ſtock'd with generous Principles than other People. They are of that ſtrain, where the Men are Valiant and Juſt, and the Women Chaſt, out of a Senſe of the Obligations they lay under by their very Birth and Extraction. They are Perſons whoſe natural Elevation of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53659:16"/> mind withholds them from ſordid Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and baſe Pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Juſtice and Charity, Mercy and Pity, Love and Benignity, are as great Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to our ſelves, as Benefits to others. But theſe excellent Virtues are never ſo beneficial to the World, as when they are improved into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Graces, and are the Fruits of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>It is the trueſt and higheſt Nobility for Men to be as great in their Piety, as in their Stations; to have the good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a good Conſcience, and not to blot their Eſcutcheons by ſtaining their Chriſtian Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>When Princes execute Juſtice and Judgment, when they deliver the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and aſſert the Cauſe of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: when they are nurſing Fathers to the Church of Chriſt, a terror to evil doers, and a praiſe to them that do well, when they walk before God with a perfect Heart, and whilſt they are enthroned upon Earth, have their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53659:16"/> Converſation in Heaven, then it is that they are <hi>Crowned with Glory and Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to the King Immortal, Inviſible, the only wiſe God, be Honour and Glory for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53659:17"/>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53659:17"/>
            <head>ANNOTATIONS.</head>
            <p>PAge 15. <hi>The Munificence of Founders and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When His Majeſty was pleaſed to command the Printing of the foregoing Sermon; the miſtake of ſome Perſons, and the ill will of others, furniſhed the Author with an <hi>Allowed Excuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The undeſerved Uſage he then met with, and his continual Diſcouragements ever ſince, have ſo far unfitted him to appear in the World; that the Preacher, and his Notes, had ſtill lain hid together in the ſame Cloſet, had not the Senſe of his Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the College that bred, and maintains him, prevailed above that of his many Defects, and the great Honour of obeying the King, in a Command, that was equally indulgent and diſpenſable.</p>
            <p>He had no other Motive to the Publication of theſe Papers, neither did he need any other, than the deſire of his honoured and worthy Collegues, to recommend in a printed Epiſtle, the preſent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to finiſh our fair Building; and our deſign of a College Hall, of which great convenience we have as yet no more than the bare Foundation.</p>
            <p>To which purpoſe, that our Paper-Meſſenger may find his way to all the liberal Hands in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he is furniſhed with a Guide, and Fellow Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers. Or elſe this firſt Note, for the ſake of which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53659:18"/> the reſt were communicated, as well as the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to which they all belong, may paſs for a Uſe of Exhortation at the end of the Sermon; as it urges the beſt practice of our Duty, and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Exerciſe of Honour; in the following Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53659:18"/>
               <head>A General Addreſs <hi>to all bountiful Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragers of Religion and Learning, in the behalf of</hi> Clare-Hall <hi>in</hi> Cambridge: <hi>which remains half built, after all the endeavours of the Society for more than Forty years to finiſh it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R College, which as to its Antiquity, is the Second in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, hath from the very Age in which it was Founded, been always <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy, either in the Ruines, or the Defects of its Building. It did at one time ſuffer ſo much by Fire, that a very conſiderable part of it (wherein were the Maſter's Lodgings, the Treaſury, and what was therein repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited of greateſt Value) was to the irreparable damage of the College conſumed.</p>
               <p>But long before that time, and when it had numbred but ſixteen years, the whole Fabrick was by a caſual Fire burnt to the ground. This occaſioned the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning of its firſt Foundation by <hi>Richard Badew</hi> (as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity Tables relate more particularly) into the hands of the incomparable Lady <hi>Elizabeth de Burgo,</hi> one of the three Co-heireſſes of <hi>Gilbert</hi> the laſt Earl of <hi>Clare</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> who beſtowed upon the then ruined Society a new College, and upon the College, unendowed before, ſuch fair Revenues, as juſtly required that it ſhould be called for ever after by her own Excellent Name.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53659:19"/>
               <p> But yet the moſt valuable part of a College, a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, was wanting for above two hundred years; till the Society had by their good Husbandry ſaved ſo much Money, as with the Gift of a hundred Pounds built one, with a fair Library over it.</p>
               <p>Within another hundred years, what our Foundreſs built for us decayed: part of it fell down: and that the College and its Inhabitants might not be buried together in the ſame Ruines, that new and unfiniſhed Fabrick we now enjoy was begun: of which, (to juſtifie Scholars, againſt thoſe that charge them with Luxury and Profuſeneſs) at leaſt one half was erected, with that Stock which many years frugality had trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured up; and with that Credit, which brought indeed a heavy Debt upon the College, but which, by the wary management of our Revenue, we have ſince diſcharged. The other, and greater part was built by the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of ſome large, and many ſmall Summs: by which charitable aſſiſtance we had fair hopes of finiſhing our College, had we not been prevented by the late Troubles.</p>
               <p>Since His Majeſties Happy Reſtauration, we have obtained an Addition; upon which, and the Avenues of our College, we have expended above two thouſand Pounds. And yet we have ſtill got no farther than half our Building, in the compleating whereof, we are now engaged.</p>
               <p>We have begun with our own private Subſcriptions: but we are unable to proceed, without thoſe liberal aids from abroad, which (without conſidering either the former products of our Education, or our future uſefulneſs to the Publick, or the ornament we ſhall add to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, or the general ſatisfaction we ſhall hereby give to Scholars, and all that favour them)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53659:19"/> the Beauty and Elegancy of our Building alone, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of other Topicks, does beg with more Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, than we our ſelves can ever command.</p>
               <p>In this Affair, we do at once both importune and ſerve our Friends, whileſt we offer to their Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the beſt of Opportunities. For as there is no diſpoſal of Wealth ſo commendable, ſo there is none ſo neceſſary, as that we now ſollicite.</p>
               <p>Since Piety, and uſeful Knowledge are of greater Conſequence to the Welfare of Mankind, than any thing in the World beſides: that ingenuous liberality which is neceſſary to the ſupport of them, is the cleareſt proof of Chriſtian ſincerity, and as much our Privilege as our Duty. Since we are Debters to Heaven for all that we are, and have; our right is undeniably for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, nay, and our Poſſeſſion too is endangered, when we fail in thoſe expreſſions of Thankfulneſs, which are all the return we can make, but are no part of Payment without the Divine Acceptilation even of the eaſie condition which entitles us to the ſatisfaction of our Redeemer, which does at once both diſcharge and renew our Debt, which makes the leaſt offering an acceptable Sacrifice, and our periſhing Riches to become an immortal Treaſure.</p>
               <p>Since we have ſo high a value for Wealth, and are ſo very unwilling to part with it, when it is againſt our Intereſt to keep it, and when we are forced to leave it; propitious Heaven, in the Opportunities of pious Munificence, has put it into our Power to be always Rich. This is the way to receive the greateſt Benefit from our moſt dangerous Enemy Wealth, which lays retrenched in the Bowels of the Earth, as if it were conſcious to its ſelf of the innumerable Miſchiefs it hath done, by its Sallies into the open World.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53659:20"/>
               <p> For Perſons of great Eſtates and Fortunes, to make no other returns of all their Plenty, but in thoſe ſhameful Exceſſes which Beaſts are never guilty of, is that which every Man, while he continues a Man, condemns: for the Wealthy to provide freely for their preſent harmleſs Satisfaction, and for the future happy Subſiſtence of their Offſpring, is what Nature, allowably enough, does ſuggeſt: but for theſe Perſons, while they deſign their Contentment, not to forget their Safety; while they ſtudy the happineſs of their Heirs, to think of their own, and to beſtow, at leaſt one Legacy upon their better part, is what Chriſtian Wiſdom does with the higheſt Reaſon dictate.</p>
               <p>So that if rich Men deſire the ſatisfaction of the beſt and trueſt Improvement of their Fortunes, if they would do all the good they can both to themſelves and others; the greateſt temporal Good they can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by the conſent of all the wiſe Men that ever lived in the World, is the Honour that is gotten by good Actions; and the greateſt good they can ever hope to do, is that diſpoſal of their Wealth, which upholds and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes the two beſt things of this World, Piety and Learning: whereby the truly Charitable will have the Happineſs, not only of future and infinite Recompences, but they will likewiſe attain that end, which is always the meaning, but never the effect of paternal Fondneſs, an Immortality here upon Earth.</p>
               <p>By this means they will inherit the juſt eſteem of wiſe Men, of ſuch as know how to uſe their Fortunes, and that do not love their Money better than themſelves. They will continue in this World, even when they are poſſeſſed of a better, and by their bountiful Donations, they will, in all ſucceeding Ages, ſtill remain here, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing the greateſt Charity, that is, inſtructing the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53659:20"/> Ignorant, reclaiming the Vicious, and relieving the Neceſſitous.</p>
               <p>The fair Monuments of their Piety will out-laſt all others: and if the World ſhould happen to ſurvive them, yet the Memory of them will not be loſt till Charity it ſelf ſhall fail. Their excellent names will not then be buried, when they ſhall become too great a weight for the Pillars that bear them: they muſt needs live, being repeated thrice every year in publick and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Commemorations, with the greateſt Honour that can be paid them by ingenuous Men; in a Society col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the diſtant parts of our own Country, from whence their Charity and Fame will be carried or ſent abroad to all others, and ſent down to all Poſterity; with the Sculpture of our Building, the Hiſtory of our Benefactors, and with the juſt, ſincere, and eternal Acknowledgments of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>The Maſter, and Fellows of</hi> Clare-Hall.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53659:21"/>
               <p> PAge 17. Japhet <hi>the eldeſt Son of</hi> Noah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We cannot conclude the reſpective Ages of the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> from the Order in which they are named. For then <hi>Ham</hi> would be the ſecond Son. But that he was the youngeſt is plain from <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. where it is related <hi>v.</hi> 22. That when <hi>Ham</hi> ſaw the nakedneſs of his Father, he told his two Brethren without: and <hi>v.</hi> 24. That when <hi>Noah</hi> awoke from his Wine, he knew what his younger Son had done unto him.</p>
               <p>Neither can <hi>Sem</hi> be the firſt-born. For <hi>Noah</hi> was ſix hundred years old when the Flood came upon the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. 6. He was five hundred years old when he begat his eldeſt Son, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 32. The Son whom at that Age he begat, could not be <hi>Sem;</hi> for he was not an hundred years old, till two years after the Deluge, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch then as <hi>Noah</hi>'s eldeſt Son was an hundred years old when he entred the Ark, and <hi>Sem</hi> was then but ninety eight; it follows evidently that <hi>Japhet</hi> muſt be the eldeſt of the Sons of <hi>Noah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Particulars are confirmed by the general Senſe of the Jewiſh Doctors. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſayes <hi>R. Salomon Jarchi,</hi> of the Sons of <hi>Noah, Japhet</hi> the laſt named, is the eldeſt. But there is better Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for the Aſſertion. The Septuagint Verſion ſays it expreſly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. 21. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. They here call <hi>Japhet</hi> in the plaineſt words can
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53659:21"/> be ſpoken, the elder Brother of <hi>Sem. Flaminius Nobilius</hi> having compared the Copies of the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint, reports their Agreement in this reading.</p>
               <p>Neither is it only in <hi>Pagnin, Arias Montanus, Tremellius,</hi> the Polyglott Interlineary, and our laſt Engliſh Tranſlation, <hi>The Brother of</hi> Japhet <hi>the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> but the Senſe, Propriety, and conſtant Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Conſtruction of the Hebrew do fully prove it. For when theſe words are to be expreſſed in the Holy Language, Sem <hi>the elder Brother of</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, it muſt be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But if we will have the forementioned words to be the Engliſh of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhall never be able to find, in any part of the Scripture, the like Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: much leſs can we tell how the Hebrew ſhould expreſs thoſe laſt words of this Text any other way, without departing from its Idiom, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving its Senſe in an ambiguous Phraſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:53659:22"/>
               <p> PAge 19. <hi>Throwing of Stones to</hi> Mercury<hi>'s Heap.</hi> If we enquire what <hi>Mercury</hi>'s Heap was, we ſhall ſee what Reaſons S. <hi>Hierom</hi> had for this ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of <hi>Prov.</hi> 26. 8. <hi>Sicut qui mittit lapidem in acervum</hi> Mercurii: <hi>ita qui tribuit honorem inſipienti.</hi> Whom our Engliſh, according to its uſual regard to him, ſhould thus follow in tranſlating the Text, As he that throweth a Stone to <hi>Mercury</hi>'s Heap; ſo is he that giveth Honour to a Fool. The pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Honour, where it is not due, is compared to the blind Idolatry of the Gentiles in worſhipping <hi>Mercury</hi> by throwing Stones to his conſecrated Pile.</p>
               <p>This is the account of the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Odyſſ.</hi> 16. which was an elevated place in that City of <hi>Ithaca,</hi> from whence <hi>Eumaeus</hi> ſaw the Rivals of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> returning.</p>
               <l>—<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtathius</hi> upon this place informs us, that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> the <hi>Thracian,</hi> who wrote a Paraphraſe upon <hi>Homer</hi> (long ſince loſt) concludes, that the place where <hi>Eumaeus</hi> had this proſpect, and which was called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, had its name from the Ceremonies of <hi>Mercury.</hi> He reports it to ſignifie beſides a heap of Stones in the Highway.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53659:22"/>
               <p> Such were the <hi>Terminales lapides</hi> among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> for ſhowing the Bounds of their Lands, which <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis, c.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Paſchalius</hi> upon a Diſtich in the firſt Elegy of <hi>Tibullus</hi> obſerves to have been adorned with Crowns and Garlands.</p>
               <p>Although there was no Statue in the place, yet every Heap of Stones was Sacred. Which Heaps were encreaſed by the ſuperſtitious Diligence of Paſſengers throwing Stones to them in Honour of <hi>Mercury.</hi> This Idolatrous Practice is mentioned in the <hi>Talmudic</hi> Book <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sanhed.</hi> c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> He that throws a Stone to <hi>Mercury,</hi> is a Perſon that commits Idolatry, for <hi>Mercury</hi> is thus worſhipped.</p>
               <p>This Pagan Rite had its Original from a Fable of <hi>Mercury,</hi> which is not commonly met withall. The Story is, that when he had killed <hi>Argus,</hi> and was to be tryed for the Fact in a Senate of the Gods, he pleaded <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Commiſſion. The Gods were thereupon afraid to condemn him: and that they might not incur the diſpleaſure of their King, they threw down thoſe Stones, by which they were to give their Suffrages, at the Feet of the Criminal: which did not only diſcharge him from Puniſhment, but was likewiſe the occaſion of the forementioned Ceremony, as well as the gathering of Votes in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature by Stones.</p>
               <p>This <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> does alſo ſignifie an Altar erected to <hi>Mercury:</hi> or the Baſis of his Image: or thoſe Stones which ſhewed the diſtances of Miles, and Furlongs: <hi>Mercury</hi> being, not only the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telar Deity, but ſaid likewiſe to have been the firſt Officer for the Highways, and to have begun the clearing of them from great Stones. Theſe Stones
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53659:23"/> were laid together by the Wayes ſide, and upon the foregoing account they were ſtiled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Mercurial Heaps.</p>
               <p>Theſe Remarques explain that old dark In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Deo Merc—</l>
                  <l>Viaco</l>
                  <l>M. Attilius</l>
                  <l>Silonis F.</l>
                  <l>Quir. Silo </l>
                  <l>Ex voto.</l>
               </q>
               <p>We have here likewiſe an Illuſtration of that paſſage in the Epigram:</p>
               <l>—Apollinis aras</l>
               <l>Arcanum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Vii—</l>
               <p>This <hi>Arcanum Vii</hi> was the myſterious Religion of the <hi>Cabiri</hi> in <hi>Samothracia:</hi> of which <hi>Cabiri Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> is reckoned for one, in that old Diſtich that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites them,</p>
               <l>Juno, Veſta, Minerva, Ceres, Diana, Venus, Mars,</l>
               <l>Mercurius, Jovi', Neptunus, Vulnanus, Apollo.</l>
               <p>We are told by <hi>Druſius</hi> out of an Arabick Book againſt the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> that it was a Practice of the <hi>Indians,</hi> to pile up Stones in Honour of their Gods. From them it was carried over into <hi>Arabia:</hi> where the worſhipping of <hi>Venus</hi> with the ſame Ceremony, was the only piece of Idolatry which <hi>Mahomet</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at <hi>Mecha.</hi> The Arabian Convert agrees to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53659:23"/> this Senſe of <hi>Salomon</hi>'s expreſſion. Neither is the forecited Paſſage one of the weakeſt Arguments for our ſubſcribing to S. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s tranſlating the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Acervum Mercurii.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why we ſhould not follow the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> and tranſlate the Hebrew Word, a <hi>Sling,</hi> we have more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over theſe Reaſons. That ſince the Hebrew Word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies a heap of Stones, ſince the Superſtition of thoſe Mercurial heaps was ſpread through the <hi>Eaſt</hi> many Ages before <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſince the very name of <hi>Mercury</hi> was formed out of this Word <hi>Margemah;</hi> ſince <hi>Manetho,</hi> though a fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Writer, is confirmed by <hi>Joſephus</hi> in his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That they were <hi>Seth</hi>'s Pillars: To interpret the expreſſion, <hi>As he that tyes a Stone in a Sling,</hi> is a ſenſe which thoſe that are beſt acquainted with the Pagan Rites, and the Jewiſh Learning, cannot admit of as the moſt obvious, true, natural, and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the wiſe Author of the ſaying.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this it is certain, that <hi>Margemah</hi> is of the ſame ſignification with <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Markolis</hi> the <hi>Talmudic</hi> name of <hi>Mercury,</hi> and of his Image or Statue. They are uſed promiſcuouſly by the old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Jewiſh Writers. The <hi>Medraſch</hi> on the Proverbs thus paraphraſes the paſſage, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Whoever honours a Fool, is like him that throws a Stone to <hi>Mercury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is not the only inſtance in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, that ſhews the Antiquity of the Pagan Idolatry. <hi>Orion</hi> and the <hi>Pleiades</hi> are mentioned by <hi>Job:</hi> Whoſe youngeſt Daughter is called in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, The Horn or Ray of Beauty, that is, ſays the verſion of the Seventy, The Horn of <hi>Amalthaea,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Job</hi> 42. 14.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53659:24"/>
               <p> In the deſolation of <hi>Babylon, Iſai</hi> 13. 21, 22. it is ſaid by the Vulgar <hi>Latin,</hi> and the <hi>Maronites, That Satyrs ſhall dance, and Sirens lodge there. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renes &amp; Daemonia illic ſalt abunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So likewiſe in <hi>Ezechiel</hi>'s Viſion, ch. 8. v. 14. <hi>At the North Door of the Temple, there ſat Women lamenting</hi> Adonis, concluded by S. <hi>Hierom</hi> to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by <hi>Tammuz. Mulieres ſedebant plangentes Adonidem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now S. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> in his ninth Homily on the <hi>Canticles,</hi> gives good ſatisfaction to thoſe that wonder at the mention of Poetick Fables in the holy Oracles of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53659:24"/>
               <p> PAge 19. <hi>There is a Pagan Empire on the further ſide of</hi> Aſia.</p>
               <p>It is that Empire where all Nobility is from Worth and Knowledge, where none are born great but thoſe of the Royal Family, where Men are honoured and advanced then only when they deſerve to be ſo.</p>
               <p>The principal Sect among them, called <hi>Jukia,</hi> hath no other charge, but to mind the buſineſs of Government, and the practice of Moral Vertues.</p>
               <p>This people, the Inhabitants of <hi>Cathaia,</hi> and the <hi>Northern China,</hi> have little Philoſophy that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, beſides Morality. Their chief Science is the Moral Contemplation of Man: In which it is their buſineſs to conſider the Offices of Princes and their Subjects, of Parents and Children, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Wives, Brethren and Friends. They have three thouſand Rules concerning Decency, Civility, Modeſty, and the Vertues of that Rank. Prudence is one of their moſt admired Vertues: And next to that they eſteem Courage, when it is imployed in the conqueſt of our ſelves.</p>
               <p>They value Juſtice, becauſe it directs us to look into our ſelves, when we determine any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring unto others: In which they place the higheſt degree of Humane Perfection. They ſay they are lovers of Vertue for no other Reaſon, but becauſe it is its own abundant Recompence. They do not concern themſelves in any enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries about future matters; alledging, they have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53659:25"/> not yet attained the knowledge of thoſe things that are before their Eyes.</p>
               <p>They underſtand little, and dote very much in Natural Philoſophy. They hold a double <hi>Metem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſychoſis,</hi> that of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and the tranſmigration of the Soul into new Paſſions and Deſires. They affirm all the Events of this Life to be Good or Evil, according to our Opinion and Judgment of them.</p>
               <p>The great things that are reported of them are credible enough, if it can be made out, That they are the Poſterity of the old <hi>Seres: Quos Luſitani perperam Sinas appellarunt,</hi> ſayes the very learned Mr. <hi>Iſ. Voſſius</hi> in his late Tract, <hi>De Art. &amp; Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiis Sinarum:</hi> And when we receive the account of their <hi>Socrates,</hi> that Divine Philoſopher <hi>Cumfuſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>Ptolemy, Mela, Pliny, Strabo, Salinus, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius</hi> and others, make the Country of the <hi>Seres</hi> to border Southward upon <hi>India</hi> without <hi>Ganges,</hi> and to be that very Tract which is now called <hi>China. Pliny</hi> taking notice of the ſimplicity of their Manners, ſays, they are very unlike their Neighbours the <hi>Scythians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe very places which <hi>Ortelius, Mercator,</hi> and the generality of Modern Geographers make the Boundaries of <hi>China,</hi> are named by the Antients as the Confines of <hi>Serae. Ptolemy</hi> ſets their Country (whoſe Metropolis, he ſayes, was called <hi>Sera)</hi> in the Neighbourhood of <hi>Scythia,</hi> on the outſide of the Mount <hi>Imaus,</hi> next <hi>India</hi> without <hi>Ganges,</hi> and on the further ſide of <hi>Aſia.</hi> The ſame ſituation is given them by <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts their Country to reach Southward as far as <hi>India, Ganges</hi> and the forenamed Mountain <hi>Imaus.</hi> In <hi>Pomponius Mela,</hi> we find the <hi>Serae,</hi> and the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53659:25"/> to be the ſame people: And that the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Saracens</hi> call the Inhabitants of <hi>Cathaia, Seres. Solinus</hi> carries us through the <hi>Scythian</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Ocean to this Country; which <hi>Pauſanias</hi> ſays, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives its name from the Worms that ſupply the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants with Silk, which according to him and others, as we find in <hi>Suidas,</hi> are called in Greek <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Seres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This appears further from their great plenty of Silk, and their skill in weaving it: Which was firſt called <hi>Serica,</hi> from their Country. Their Art is thus ſet out by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> in his <hi>Periegeſis,</hi> v. 755.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Weaving rich colour'd Robes they Flowers ſtrow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such as Dame Natures Tapiſtry does ſhow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such as the Spiders fineſt Art out-go.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>There have been thoſe Opinions, and Reports of their great Antiquity, that might give ſome occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the vaſt Extravagancies of the <hi>Chineſe Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology.</hi> They are the oldeſt people that were known to <hi>Pliny: Primi ſunt hominum qui noſcantur Seres,</hi> is his account of them. And <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Book <hi>De Cultu foem.</hi> ſays they were Weavers, <hi>Ab initio rerum,</hi> from the beginning of the World. <hi>Primos hominum Seres cognoſcimus,</hi> are the Words of <hi>Julius Solinus,</hi> The <hi>Seres</hi> we know to be the firſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Men.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53659:26"/>
               <p> Beſides this, the exact ſimilitude of Temper, in the Hiſtorical Accounts of both, is a ſufficient Argument of their being the ſame people. The beſt deſcription of the <hi>Seres,</hi> we have from <hi>Euſebius</hi> in theſe Words: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Law of the <hi>Seres</hi> is againſt Murdering, Whoring, Thieving, and all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images. And in that moſt ſpacious Country you ſhall not ſee a Shrine, a Fornicatreſs, an Adultreſs, a Thief arraigned, a Murderer tryed, a Man ſlain. <hi>(He goes on diſputing againſt Fate.)</hi> The Influence of <hi>Mars</hi> belching Fire from the midſt of Heaven, hath never forced the Liberty of any mans Will to give a fatal Stab to another. The Conjunction of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> did never force any Man in that Region to an adulterous Embrace, though <hi>Mars</hi> is there to be ſeen in the midſt of the Heavens every day, and in every hour of the day there are Children born among the <hi>Seres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like Citation of <hi>Vigerus</hi> in a Note upon this Paſſage, may be ſuppoſed to be taken from an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of good Credit and Antiquity, though he does not name him.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Seres</hi> were the Anceſtors of the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes,</hi> appears in other Inſtances. The <hi>Chineſes</hi> wear no Weapons, travel without Arms, and have little or no eſteem for Soldiers. The like account we have from <hi>Strabo</hi> of the <hi>Seres:</hi> that they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53659:26"/> reckoned it a crime for men to exerciſe themſelves <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the Arts of War. He likewiſe mentions their <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their Frugality, and Healthfulneſs. As <hi>Lucian,</hi> when he ſpeaks of the moſt long-liv'd Nations, names the <hi>Seres</hi> in the firſt place, and aſcribes their Longevity to their Temperance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> tells us they lived quietly, Strangers to Arms and Wars, <hi>nulli finit imorum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſti,</hi> troubleſome to none of their Neighbours, the moſt frugal of all Nations in a moſt plentiful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that they ſtudied the tranquillity of Life, and avoided the Converſation of the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mites quidem,</hi> ſays <hi>Pliny</hi> of them, they were meek People, but fled from Strangers like Beaſts, and had no Communication of Language with any other Country. To which <hi>Solinus</hi> adds, that they traded with Merchants without verbal Conference, <hi>Mercium pretia oculis aeſtimantes,</hi> buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling with their Eyes, and allowing Merchants only to croſs their firſt River. This is the ſame Character that we find of them in <hi>Stephanus de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbibus,</hi> namely that they were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a People that would not mingle with other Societies.</p>
               <p>This ſhieneſs and averſion to Strangers was found to be the temper of the <hi>Chineſes</hi> by <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Paulus Venetus,</hi> who firſt diſcovered them to the <hi>Europaeans;</hi> and is confirmed by many others, who give us ſurprizing Relations of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and Honeſty of the <hi>Chineſes</hi> in the days of their great Maſter of Morals <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>,</hi> and in the Ages after him.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53659:27"/>
               <p> The <hi>Chinenſian Socrates C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>,</hi> by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of his admirable Philoſophy, did work a perfect Reformation in the Manners of the People. He reſtored the uſe of Weights and Meaſures, the decence of Funerals, the duty of Children in maintaining their indigent Parents, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of Merchants in their Affairs. He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with the Men of the Age to be juſt and kind; and the Women to be chaſt, humble, and quiet.</p>
               <p>He brought the whole Empire to the Temper of a ſingle well-ordered Family. They had for one another the tenderneſs of Parents, the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Brethren, and the ſincerity of the beſt Friends. Nothing could be loſt in the Country: but whatever was dropt upon the Highway, was always left there by thoſe that found it, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Owner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Strabo</hi> ſays as much of the <hi>Seres</hi> in the ſame Age, that they had the ſtricteſt Juſtice, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Proceſs even againſt bad Language. That they ſhould ſo far exceed their Poſterity the modern <hi>Chineſes,</hi> who are now laſcivious, malicious, and falſe Pretenders to Virtue, will be no matter of wonder to us, when we ſhall have conſidered either the Doctrine or the Perſon of their excellent Tutor, the oriental <hi>Socrates,</hi> the Divine <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53659:27"/>
               <head>He thus begins his firſt Book.</head>
               <p>TÁ HIŎ CHĪ TÁO SÁI MIM̑ MIM̑ JĔ SAÍ SIN̄ ḾIǸ SAÍ CHÍ YŪ XEŃ CHĪ CHÌ HEÚ YEÙ TIḾ TĪM HEÚ NEM̑ SIM̀ SIḾ LH HEÚ NÉM̀ NGĀN NGĀN LH HEÚ NÉM̀ LIÚ̇ LIÚ̇ LH HEÚ NEM̑ TĔ UÆ̆ YEÙ PUEǸ MŎ MŎ SÚ YEÙ CHŪḾ XÌ CHĪ SÒ SIĒN HEÚ SÉ KIŃ TÁO Ỳ. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The intent of great Men in Knowledge and Inſtruction, does conſiſt in the enlightning of our Spiritual Power conveyed to us from Heaven, by the Virtues. It does conſiſt in renewing the World by Exhortation and Example. It conſiſts in ſetling firmly upon the chiefeſt good. When People know wherein they are to ſettle, then they have the end. When they have reſolved themſelves in the end, then they can be at reſt. When their mind is at reſt, then they can ſtrengthen it. When they have ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Mind, then they can diſtinguiſh Good from Evil. When they have made this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then they can attain the end, by acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Reaſon. There is in things that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53659:28"/> which is more and leſs Excellent, as the Body and the Branches in the Tree. Affairs have an end and a beginning. To obtain effectively the perfection of Good, is the end; to know where we are to ſettle firmly, is the beginning. To know thoſe things that are to be preferred, and thoſe that are to be undervalued, is to approach to the knowledge of great Men.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His next Paragraph is this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>When the Ancients would make proof of the Spiritual Power in Government, they took care in the firſt place to govern their Kingdoms well: when they would govern their Kingdoms well, their firſt care was the right ordering of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies: when they would order their Families well, it was their firſt buſineſs, to attire their own Perſons with the Ornaments of Virtue: when they would deck themſelves with the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, they firſt faſhioned their Hearts: when they would faſhion their Hearts, they firſt confirmed their Intentions in the baniſhing of every diſguiſe: when they would confirm their Intentions, they would firſt enlarge their Underſtandings: which enlargement of the Underſtanding, conſiſteth in the compriſing of Matters, in forecaſting buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in making a convenient proviſion for every preſent occaſion; or rather by penetrating that moſt perfect Harmony of Nature in Humane Reaſon. For when Matters are dived into, the perfection of Knowledge is attained: when the perfection of Knowledge is attained, the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is confirmed: when the Intention is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53659:28"/> the Heart is rightly managed: when the Heart is managed, the Man is compleated: when the Man is compleated, the Family is rightly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: when the Family is rightly ordered, then the Kingdom is well governed: when our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms are well governed, the Empire will be alſo peaceable and calm.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This is the beginning of the firſt Treatiſe in the former part of <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi>'s Works, being a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the Perfection of Man, and of Government. In his other Tracts, there are many excellent Moral Diſcourſes, the ſtile whereof ſhows the <hi>Chineſe</hi> Eloquence to conſiſt chiefly in <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maxes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Writings have leſs Art, but more of the true Spirit of Morality, than is to be found in <hi>Plato</hi> himſelf, and the moſt eſteemed of the old Greek and Roman Moraliſts. He has other Books of Dialogues, Odes, Sentences, and Moral Diſſerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. He wrote the Annals of the <hi>Chineſe</hi> Kings from <hi>Fohi,</hi> who according to their Chronology liv'd before <hi>Moſes.</hi> He wrote of Political Virtues, of Court days and Vacations, of Preſages; of the Rewards of good Men, and the Puniſhments of the Wicked: and upon many other Subjects. It was his Motto, <hi>Lay nothing upon another, that you would not bear your ſelf.</hi> Like a true <hi>Socrates,</hi> he aſſerted and worſhipped the one true God. He commonly invoked Heaven, but in a Metonymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Senſe. Which we have the more reaſon to believe, becauſe the <hi>Chineſes</hi> in his time had no Idols.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53659:29"/>
               <p> He is thought to have propheſied of our Saviour Chriſt: for he would always diſown his own Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and refuſe the Commendations of his Piety with this reply, SĪ FAM̄ YEÙ XIḾ GIȖ, <hi>The Holy one is to be looked for in the Weſt.</hi> Fifty years after our Saviour, one of their Emperors moved by this Tradition, and by a Dream, that there came and appeared before him out of the Weſt a God-like Man, ſent ſome Perſons of his Court to make enquiry after the true Law: who wanting either courage or skill to ſail further than the Red-Sea, brought home, and firſt planted in <hi>China</hi> the Idolatry of the adjoyning Countries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi> was born above five hundred years before Chriſt, about the beginning of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchy, and probably was contemporary with <hi>Cyrus.</hi> At nineteen years of Age he married, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a few years buried his Wife, continued ſingle.</p>
               <p>He never uſed Concubines, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of his Country. His Life was every way an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his Diſcourſes. His Moderation and Piety, his conſtant watchfulneſs over himſelf, his contempt of Riches, Honours, and Dangers, his unwearied Induſtry in propagating Moral Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is to be read in his Books, as well as in the Stories of his Life.</p>
               <p>He is ſtill had in ſo great Veneration by his Country-men, that the great Office of <hi>Mandarin</hi> hath been always choſen out of his Family, which to this very Age hath been exempted from Tribute. His Books uſe to be read every where throughout the Country, and his Philoſophy taught in all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Cities of <hi>China.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53659:29"/>
               <p> There is an ingenious Merchant, a Fellow of the Royal Society, who hath put into the hands of one of his Collegues, ſeveral of <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi>'s Books, brought from <hi>Siam,</hi> where they were printed, in order to an Engliſh Edition of them, and of a <hi>Lexicon</hi> and <hi>Clavis</hi> to the Language, and to a new World of Learning.</p>
               <p>The foregoing Specimen is ſent abroad, to give ſome account of thoſe great Rarities, and to quicken the publication of them; out of a juſt reſpect to the worthy Owner of the only Copies in this part of the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53659:30"/>
               <p> PAge 23. <hi>That Chriſtian Charity which thinketh no Evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. Charity ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth no evil. Where the caſe is doubtful (ſayes <hi>Grotius</hi> upon the place) it always interprets in the beſt Senſe.</p>
               <p>It thinketh no evil either of Superiors, or Equals, where it ſees none. According to the excellent temper of the Laws by which our Nation is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned; it preſumes every Man to be good, who does not appear to be otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>But ever ſince Man degenerated, it hath been the greateſt part of his temporal Miſery, to eſteem him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upright and wiſe, and other Men Villains and Sots. Which makes him diſobedient to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and unjuſt to his Neighbours. He looks upon his Neighbours as Dotterels, and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours as Harpies. He reckons it as eaſie to catch the former, as difficult to eſcape the deadly Talons of the latter.</p>
               <p>Since the time that Men had reaſon to be afraid of one another, their Fears have undone them. Ever ſince they have been unable to govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they have been afraid of their Rulers: leſt they ſhould invade their Properties, and by altering their Religion, make way to their Civil Rights.</p>
               <p>Through the want of Chriſtian Charity, and that Faith from whence it proceeds, People are ſo void of good Thoughts, and ſo full of jealous Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; they have ſo great a concern for their Pelf,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53659:30"/> and ſo little truſt in the Providence of God, that when their Fortunes are as ſafe as if they were the only care of Heaven; for ſeditious Men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them that their Prince will have no regard to Rules and Conſtitutions, but intends to govern them by Arbitrary and lawleſs Adminiſtrations, they have no more to do, but only to tell them ſo.</p>
               <p>Upon the firſt ſtrong report, they believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Slaves: and indeed they are ſo, to their own Paſſions. They feel more ſmart from their own Fears, than they can ſuffer under the Whips of Infidels. For want of crueller Maſters, they become Tyrants to themſelves.</p>
               <p>Rags and Priſons with a quieter mind would be great Bleſſings to them. For they are of a Temper which makes Proſperity an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Plague. They that have nothing to loſe are in a much happier con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. For Poverty is not ſo great an Evil, as the fear of falling into it.</p>
               <p>But the great Riddle is, that theſe Men ſhould be wounded and tortured, by that which never touched them, by ſomething at a diſtance from them, which they cannot prove by one Argument will ever be nearer: nay which hath nothing at all of Beeing, more than it received from their diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Imaginations, yet frights and diſtracts them, more than any thing that is real and certain.</p>
               <p>It is indeed very ſtrange for a Kingdom to be thunder-ſtruck by an undiſcernable clap of Tyranny that melts and conſumes all the Rights of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and yet not one Man hurt in his Perſon or Fortunes.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53659:31"/>
               <p> The true State of the Caſe is this. When the guilty Conſcience tells a Man plainly what uſe he himſelf would make of Soveraign Power: when the Wretch hath done all the Miſchief he can to his Inferiors; and has thought wickedly of his Prince, that he is altogether ſuch an one as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 'tis no wonder that he fears Him firſt, and then hates Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is the account</hi> of all the Commotions, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, Seditions, and Confuſions that ever yet were, or perhaps ever will be raiſed by diſcontented or ſeduced Perſons in all the Governments of the World. When deſigning Miſcreants undertake the embroiling of their Country, the People ferment immediately upon the bare report of approaching Slavery.</p>
               <p>They believe all that is told them, unleſs it be then, when it happens that there is any thing of truth in the Relation. Where there is any juſt cauſe of ſuſpicion and miſtruſt, they are everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſecure. It is an expence of thinking too great for their ſtock, to examine the following Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p>Whether their Governours have not been injured by the malicious and crafty Inſinuations of ſome bad Men?</p>
               <p>Whether they have any better, or other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than their own confidence, that they are not impoſed upon?</p>
               <p>Whether the Grievances which their Leaders make ſo great a noiſe with, be any other than the Neceſſities which their chargeable Vices have brought upon them?</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53659:31"/>
               <p> How it comes to paſs, that the Evils which terrifie and afflict them, which are ſaid to grow and encreaſe upon them every day, are commonly huſht and untalkt of, and laid aſleep for ſuch long Intervals, and never heard of but from Male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in ſome high Conteſt with the Government; that the popular clamour of Grievances ſhould prove the moſt dangerous ſort of Thunder, and never be heard but in times of great Heat?</p>
               <p>In a few words, what ſhould be the reaſon, that in a Country which in its own Productions, and in foreign Supplies, in the eaſineſs of its Government, in the Wealth, Safety, and Priviledges of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, exceeds all other upon the face of the Earth; in a time of Peace, and open Trade, and univerſal Proſperity, there ſhould be thoſe ſudden hideous outcries of Grievances, preſſing to death the Men that do not feel them, nor underſtand what is meant by the word, nor know what to complain of, till they are inſtructed by the idolized Mutineers?</p>
               <p>The Credulity, Fickleneſs, and Levity of the common People, have in all former Ages been the Engines with which politick Atheiſts have ruined the beſt Governments. Neither is it a Prophecy, but a clearer proſpect of an effect in its unhappy Cauſes, to ſay, that ſcarce any Country will be embroiled hereafter without this old Artifice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of this Weapon, which after all the execution it hath done in the World, is ſtill as ſharp as ever, and will never want an edge as long as there is Ambition and Revenge to whet it.</p>
               <p>This hath always been the temper of the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, in all times and places by the juſt judgment of the Almighty upon their diſobedience to God and Man.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53659:32"/>
               <p> Upon any noiſe of Oppreſſion and Tyranny, though the Alarm be never ſo falſe, the People fall immediately into the cold and hot Fits of an incurable State-Quartan, they are preſently light-headed, and preſently after ſtark raving Mad.</p>
               <p>That the pretended danger of Tyranny and Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, or an Invaſion of the Peoples Rights, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious or Civil, hath been the chief, and for the moſt part, the only Incentive to all the Sedition that ever diſturbed the Peace of Kingdoms and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, in any Age or Country whoſe Records have come to our hands, may be concluded from the following <hi>Inſtances;</hi> and proved by thouſands more, <hi>ready to be produced.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:53659:32"/>
               <head>THE INSTANCES.</head>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <p>WHen <hi>Ariſtagoras</hi> was endeavouring to ſtrengthen the <hi>Ionian</hi> Faction, being the Perſon who headed that People when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> he uſed this To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick, when he urged <hi>Cleomenes</hi> King of <hi>Sparta</hi> to joyn with him in his Rebellion. There is (ſays he) a deſign to introduce a deſpotical Government, and to ſeize the <hi>Ionian</hi> Liberties. Therefore in the name of the <hi>Graecian</hi> Gods, redeem the <hi>Ionians</hi> from Slavery.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Hannibal</hi> invaded <hi>Italy,</hi> at his croſſing the <hi>Alpes,</hi> he made a long Speech to his Army. Which, when the Hiſtorian reported, he poliſht the ſenſe of one part of it, in theſe Expreſſions. That Wealth which the <hi>Romans</hi> poſſeſs, and which hath been the vaſt Gain of ſo many triumphant Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, 'tis all yours, and the owners of it into the bargain. Draw your Swords for thoſe mighty Spoils in the name of the aſſiſting Gods. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the War, and march into <hi>Italy</hi> with our infeſting Banners, being like to prove as much the bolder Warriours, as the hopes are greater, and the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions ſtronger in him that makes the Aſſault, than in the Man that oppoſes it. Beſides our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53659:33"/> Courage is raiſed by Diſcontents, Wrongs, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities. I, your Commander, in the firſt place, then you all that were to beſiege <hi>Saguntum,</hi> ſhould have been demanded to undergo the moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Tortures. Theſe Men, the cruelleſt, and proudeſt in the World, purſue their own ends in every thing that is Arbitrary.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Athenians</hi> had begun a War with <hi>Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,</hi> they endeavoured to bring over the <hi>Camarines</hi> to their Alliance. <hi>Hermocrates</hi> being then employed in the Embaſſy of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> alledges, that the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Expedition would in the event be fatal, not only to <hi>Camarana,</hi> but to all <hi>Sicily.</hi> It is his whole buſineſs to lay open the <hi>Athenian</hi> Deſigns, beginning at the very Original of their Government. The <hi>Athenians</hi> (ſayes he) come into <hi>Sicily,</hi> with that pretence which you have been told of, but with that intention which we all do now ſuſpect: not to reſtore the <hi>Leontines</hi> to their Country, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to make themſelves Maſters of ours. You have then your choice: either certain Slavery with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the hazard of a War; or joynt hopes with us of a Conqueſt, which will deliver you from thoſe baſe Maſters, and from our perpetual Enmity.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Mucianus</hi> a Malecontent under the Reign of <hi>Vitellius,</hi> had a deſign to ſet up another Emperor, he thus urged <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> to depoſe <hi>Vitellius,</hi> and to take upon him the Government. They that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate upon great Attempts, ſhould firſt compute, whether that which they undertake is profitable to the Commonwealth, honourable to themſelves, eaſie, or at leaſt probable to be effected. O <hi>Veſpaſian!</hi> I invite you to an Imperial Charge, which will be as advantageous to the Publick, as glorious to your
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53659:33"/> ſelf. We are not to encounter that acuteſt Wit of the deified <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> nor that moſt wary Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the aged <hi>Tiberius,</hi> nor the Family of <hi>Caius,</hi> or <hi>Claudius,</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> ſetled in the Government by long Poſſeſſion. Beſides the enduring of thoſe, you did likewiſe yield to the Nobility of <hi>Galba.</hi> But to be ſtill careleſs, and to ſuffer the Commonwealth to be infected, and deſtroyed, would be ſtupid ſloth, though you were ſure your Slavery would continue as ſafe, as it is ignominious.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Lithuanians</hi> rebelled againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor <hi>Valentinian,</hi> he was aſſiſted by the <hi>Franks</hi> in their Suppreſſion: and he rewarded their Service by ten years Exemption from their cuſtomary Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. Which time being expired, they refuſed to ſubmit to their former Taxes. Hereupon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror having fought, and defeated them, drove them out of their Country: inſomuch that they were forced to follow their Commander <hi>Marcomir</hi> into a part of <hi>Germany,</hi> to which they gave the name of <hi>Franconia.</hi> Being aſſembled to conſider what form of Government would be fitteſt for them, <hi>Quadrek,</hi> one of their greateſt Lords, ſtands up at the Debate, and ſpeaks thus in favour of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracy.</hi> It is the hardeſt thing in the World to find a King or a Prince that is duely accompliſhed: but ſuppoſe we could be furniſhed with one that hath all the Perfections requiſite to a Throne, yet there is danger ſtill, that this Perſon, after ſome time, may come to make his Will his Law, and fall off to Licentiouſneſs and Tyranny. After many of the common, and fully anſwered Arguments againſt Monarchy, he ends thus. But foraſmuch as I find the Herald going to proclaim <hi>Pharamond</hi> King, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53659:34"/> in ſo doing, to aſſiſt at the Funerals of the name of <hi>Franks,</hi> for my part, that my Eyes may eſcape the ſight of that miſerable fatal Ceremony, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part immediately into a voluntary Exile, in which I ſhall rather chooſe to end my days, than to live here, and ſee the Native Liberty of my Country deſtroyed, the Equity of the Laws trodden under foot, inſulting Tyranny ſet up, and all of us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to endleſs Slavery. To this Harangue the Hiſtorian ſubjoyns <hi>Pharamond</hi>'s reply in an excellent defence of <hi>Monarchy.</hi> Amongſt other things, he ſhows the Benefits of that Form of Government; and that the Liberty of the People conſiſts in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Prince: for which obedience they can no more be called Slaves, than thoſe Seamen who in a Tempeſt obſerve the orders of their Pilot.</p>
                  <p>When Count <hi>Candidian</hi> was commiſſioned by the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius</hi> to keep the Peace and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Tumults at the Council of <hi>Epheſus:</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great Favourer of the <hi>Neſtorian</hi> Faction, gave order for ſtopping all Packets, both by Sea and Land, that no Letters might paſs to inform the Emperor, or any other Perſon of what was tranſacted in the Synod. But he himſelf in the mean time, writes to the Emperor againſt <hi>Cyrill,</hi> and other Biſhops. Firſt he throws this Calumny upon them, that they were ſo overhaſty in opening the Aſſembly, that they would not ſtay for the arrival of <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch.</hi> Then he belies them, and ſayes, that all the Biſhops that were at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> were not at the Synod, that they were not all ſummoned, and that there were Differences among thoſe that were preſent. With theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Count <hi>Candidian, Neſtorius</hi> ſends his to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53659:34"/> the Emperor to the ſame effect and deſign, only with this difference, that <hi>Neſtorius</hi> patched up more lies, which he ſet off with that variety of fair Pretences, that they would eaſily find belief with Perſons unacquainted with the Proceedings. That profligate Jugler, in his Epiſtle to the Emperor, repreſents himſelf, not only as a Profeſſor of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith, but as a moſt reſolute Defender of it: and craftily pretends, that he came to <hi>Epheſus</hi> purely upon that account. In relating the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of the Synod, he begins with the fouleſt Lyes. He denies that the Biſhops of <hi>Egypt</hi> were willing to ſtay for <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> who had ſent Meſſengers to give them notice that he ſhould quickly arrive. He adds, that the Biſhops of the contrary Party had acted Tyrannically, had given out Menaces, had diſperſed their Guards about the City to raiſe Tumults, and that they came ſhouting to his Houſe, and threatned to kill him. That the Leader of them all was <hi>Memnon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Then he complained that all the Churches of <hi>Epheſus</hi> were ſhut againſt him, and that he had not ſo much as the liberty to take the Communion. Upon theſe, and ſuch like cunning Suggeſtions, he petitions the Emperor (for all his Deſigns and ſtrongeſt Efforts drove at that) to iſſue out Orders for adjuſting the number of the Synod: in which he pretended there were wanting two Biſhops out of every Province. In the concluſion, as if he had been cruelly oppreſſed by the Orthodox, he ends his Letter with this Expreſſion: If we cannot prevail for this, we deſire only that care may be taken for our ſafe return to our ſeveral Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for they threaten our very Lives. He was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53659:35"/> ſubtle in his requeſt; deſiring to be ſent back to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> when he had been depoſed from that See: a piece of Craft like his Petition for a new Council, when he was already condemned in one lawfully aſſembled. There ſubſcribed with him to this Epiſtle, to gain him the greater Credit, nine Biſhops, all rank <hi>Neſtorians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When that Incendiary <hi>Catiline</hi> had plotted the Ruine of the Government, and of <hi>Cicero,</hi> in his Letter to <hi>Q. Marcius,</hi> among other things alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as bad, he writes thus. We call God and Man to witneſs, that we have not armed our ſelves either againſt our Country, or to invade others; but only to ſecure our own Perſons from Injuries: whilſt by the Prevalency and Cruelty of Uſurers we are miſerable, and neceſſitous: moſt of us are kept out of our Country, but all of us out of our Offices and Eſtates. There is not a Man among us, who according to his Hereditary Right, can have the Benefit of the Laws; or when he hath loſt his Patrimony can keep his Liberty. We do not ask for Power or Riches, which are the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of all the Wars and Conteſts that diſturb Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, but for Liberty, which no good Man is willing to loſe ſooner than his Life. He encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages thoſe that were engaged with him in his Conſpiracy with theſe Expreſſions. What I have been contriving, I have told you ſeparately: but ſince that Communication, every day, hath put my thoughts into a greater heat, when I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that condition of Life which we are to expect, unleſs we recover our Liberties. Rouze your ſelves then! and open your Eyes upon that fair object you have ſo often wiſhed to ſee, your
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53659:35"/> Liberty. Your Affairs, your Opportunities, your Dangers, your Poverty, and the noble Spoils of War, will perſwade you better than my Oratory. I offer my ſelf to you to be either your General, or your Fellow-Soldier: neither my Mind, nor my Body ſhall ever be wanting to your Service. I hope I ſhall aſſiſt you in theſe Affairs as your Conſul, unleſs I am wrong in my account, and that you are better prepared for Slavery than Empire.</p>
                  <p>When the Mechanicks of <hi>Florence,</hi> and eſpecially the Weavers, were grown jealous of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, in the Reign of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt: after many private Meetings in the night, one of the boldeſt of them exhorts his Companions to perſevere in their Sedition with this Harangue. Were we now, my Fellow-Soldiers, to conſider, whether we ſhould betake our ſelves to our Arms, whether we ſhould fire the neighbouring Houſes, and plunder the very Temples themſelves, I ſhould vote with thoſe who would be for adviſing further upon it: and it may be, I ſhould rather chuſe ſecure Poverty, than dangerous and uncertain Gains. But foraſmuch as we have drawn our Swords, and committed very many Outrages, I ſuppoſe we have nothing elſe now to determine, but the courſe we ſhall take to defend our ſelves 'till we can ſecure our Indemnity. I can eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we had no ground but our Poverty for the Reſolutions we have taken. Yet ſince the whole City is in an uproar, and all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants are got together to deſtroy us, ſince there are ſo many extraordinary Aſſemblies of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53659:36"/> the Lords and Magiſtrates to contrive a way to enſnare us, and to make themſelves ſtrong enough to cut us off, there are two things eſpecially that we are to take care of. One, that we may not be called to an account for what we have done within a few days paſt: the other, that for the time to come, we may live in a better enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Liberties, and more to our content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore that we may gain an Act of Pardon for our paſt Crimes, it is my opinion that we muſt commit new ones: which muſt be ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated by Burning, Plundering, and ſuch like Barbarities: in which we muſt get as great a number of Accomplices as we can. For where multitudes offend, it is rare to have particular Perſons ſingled out for puniſhment. By this means a way will be opened for us, to gain thoſe Points that will ſupport our Liberties.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Moors</hi> of <hi>Granada,</hi> under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of <hi>Jacob Almanſor</hi> the <hi>Saracen,</hi> were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing themſelves of the Provinces between the <hi>Pyrenees</hi> and the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> the event of the War was for a long time doubtful. And though the <hi>Moors</hi> were conquered in the Field, yet in their minds they remained impregnable. The greateſt part of them, to ſecure their Goods and Eſtates, with the moſt execrable diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, pretended to be Chriſtians, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in <hi>Andaluzia.</hi> But preſſed with the Kings Edicts concerning Religion, and remaining ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in the Superſtition of their Country, they retreated into the neighbouring Mountains, and lived by Theft and Robbery. <hi>France</hi> being
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53659:36"/> then embroiled, and the Arms of <hi>Spain</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed againſt the rebelling <hi>Netherlands.</hi> The <hi>Moors</hi> took this opportunity to appoint private Conventions. All Ages and Conditions of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple among them, ſent their Burgeſſes to <hi>Cales.</hi> There did they agree upon the methodizing, and timing their Conſpiracy. It was ordered in their Aſſembly, that their deſign ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by Widowers to Widowers, by Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands to Husbands, and by young Bachelors to thoſe of their own condition. The Seaſon pitcht upon is Winter, and <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> judged the fitteſt time: when the nights are long, when the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities of the Feſtival fill the Churches, and empty the Houſes: when the Kings Ships lay diſperſed in ſeveral Havens, without Soldiers, and with a few Sailers: this was their fitteſt opportunity for deſcending from the Mountains without making a noiſe. They hold a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: where <hi>Ferdinando Caguer</hi> thus applies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to their Unconſtancy and Fears. How long, O my Friends, Collegues, and Fellow-Soldiers, ſhall we ſuffer our ſelves to be baffled, by means of our ſlothfulneſs! How long ſhall the moſt petulant of Mankind treat us like People of a ſervile Condition, nay and worſe than Slaves. Our Wives, Children, Eſtates, are wholly at their diſpoſal: neither after ſo many Ages, and a Servitude imbittered with the ſevereſt Preſſures, does any hope of Liberty dawn upon us. New Burdens, new Contributions, new Taxes, are daily impoſed upon us. As many Tenants as there are in the City, ſo many of the cruelleſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53659:37"/> Tyrants do we feel galling our Necks. We miſerable Wretches are forbidden commerce with God and Man. Among the Chriſtians we paſs for <hi>Moriſco</hi>'s, and are charged with their abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Errors: among the <hi>Moors</hi> we are ſuſpected for Chriſtians, inſomuch that they will not give us a word, nor beſtow an Almes upon us, nor make a Bargain with us. We therefore, becauſe we keep our Faith, and purchaſe a miſerable Life by a ſlaviſh Obedience, are afflicted on all ſides: We are not more odious to one Party, than ſuſpected by another.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Milaneſes</hi> had been at War with the Emperor <hi>Frederick</hi> for a long time, and with various Succeſs; they were at length conquered, and their City beſieged. Being forced to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon Diſcretion, the Emperor, to prevent their future reſiſtance, raſed their City. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the principal Cities of <hi>Lombardy</hi> entred into a League, to re-build and fortifie <hi>Milan:</hi> whereunto they bound themſelves by a Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Oath, which contained an hypocritical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Faith and Allegiance to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror. When this <hi>dutiful Rebellion</hi> was debated by the Deputies of the ſeveral Cities of <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardy,</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>James</hi> at <hi>Pontida</hi> in <hi>Breſciano,</hi> they were ſetled in their deſign by the Diſcourſe of <hi>Pinamonte Vimercato,</hi> in which there were theſe Paſſages. I do believe that every one of you Brethren, Friends, and Repreſentatives of our moſt loving and faithful Allies, knows perfectly the Devaſtations, Ruines, Murders, Robberies and Violences acted upon every Sex
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53659:37"/> and Age; the Gabels, Grievances, and Wrongs done us by <hi>Frederick,</hi> and other barbarous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons commiſſioned by him, naturally Enemies to the <hi>Italian</hi> name. But foraſmuch as this evil Plant is not yet fully rooted, I ſuppoſe our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Union may deliver us from the perpetuity of that Slavery which grows every day more Heavy and Cruel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:53659:38"/>
                  <head>The Parallel, Inſtances in the beginning, and Progreſs of the late Rebellion.</head>
                  <p>THE Lord <hi>Digby</hi> in his Speech for triennial Parliaments, <hi>Jan.</hi> 19. 1640. complains that The Liberty and Property of the Subject, is fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally ſubverted, and raviſht away by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of a pretended Neceſſity.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> in the beginning of his Speech againſt Epiſcopacy, <hi>Feb.</hi> 9. 1640. ſayes it does en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench upon the Rights and Liberties of the Subject, as well as thoſe of the Crown.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Waller</hi> in his Speech before the Commons 1640. upon the King's demand of a Supply, hath this Paſſage: Let us give new Force to the many Laws which have been heretofore made for the maintaining of our Rights and Privileges; and to reſtore this Nation to its fundamental and vital Liberties, the Propriety of our Goods, and freedom of our Perſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Denzill Holles</hi> at a Committee of both Houſes in the Painted Chamber <hi>May</hi> 4. 1641. ſpeaks theſe words: They find <hi>(viz.</hi> the Commons) Jeſuits and Prieſts conſpiring with ill Miniſters of State to deſtroy our Religion: they find ill Miniſters conjoyned together to ſubvert our Laws and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53659:38"/>
                  <p> Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> in his Speech for aboliſhing Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy urges, that it is prejudicial to the Civil State, as having ſo powerful and ill an Influence upon our Laws, the Prerogative of the King, and the Liberties of the Subject.</p>
                  <p>In the Articles againſt Sir <hi>Richard Bolton</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>Ireland, John</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> Sir <hi>Gerrard Lowther,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Radcliffe,</hi> this was the Leader, that they intending the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Commonwealth of this Realm, have traiterouſly confederated and conſpired together to ſubvert the Fundamental Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdom, and in purſuance thereof, they and every of them have traiterouſly contrived, introduced and exerciſed an arbitrary and tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Government againſt Law throughout this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by the Countenance and Aſſiſtance of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> then chief Governour of this Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Article of the Impeachment of the Lord Keeper <hi>Finch</hi> was, that the ſaid <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Finch</hi> hath traiterouſly and wickedly endeavoured to ſubvert the Fundamental Laws and eſtabliſhed Government of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and inſtead thereof, to introduce an arbitrary, tyrannical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment againſt Law, which he hath declared by traiterous and wicked Words, Counſels, Opinions, Judgments, Practices and Actions.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Article begins the Impeachment of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> after the reading whereof, Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> in his Speech upon it, hath theſe words: If this Treaſon had taken effect, our Souls had been enſlaved to the ſpiritual Tyranny of Satan; our Conſciences to the Eccleſiaſtical Tyranny of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53659:39"/> Pope; our Lives, Perſons, and Eſtates to the Civil Tyranny of an arbitrary, unlimited, confuſed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
                  <p>The Speeches in the Parliament of the Third year of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, delivered by Sir <hi>Francis Seymour,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Philips,</hi> Sir <hi>Benj. Rudyard,</hi> and many others, which are of the ſame note and ſtrain with thoſe already mentioned, are more eaſily met with: and therefore the Reader is referred to them in the firſt Volum of Mr. <hi>Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s Collections.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe of <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> are greater Rarities: and therefore it will not be amiſs to pick out ſome of the Flowers in two or three of them.</p>
                  <p>His Speech in the Painted Chamber at his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the Parliament <hi>Jan.</hi> 22. 1654. hath theſe <hi>fine ſtrokes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Page 17. Religion was not the thing at the firſt contended for: but God brought it to that Iſſue at laſt, and gave it unto us by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy: and at laſt it proves to be that which was moſt dear unto us: and wherein conſiſted this, more than in obtaining that Liberty from the Tyranny of Biſhops, to all Species of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, to worſhip God according to their own Light and Conſciences?</p>
                  <p>Page 18. Thoſe that were ſound in the Faith, how proper was it for them to labour for Liberty, for a juſt Liberty, that Men ſhould not be tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon for their Conſciences!</p>
                  <p>Page 27.—Though ſome may think it a hard thing, without Parliamentary Authority to raiſe Money; yet I have another Argument, from the good of the People of this Nation, if they would be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53659:39"/> ſafe, and have no better Principle: whether they prefer the having of their will, though it be to their deſtruction, rather than comply with things of neceſſity: that will excuſe me.</p>
                  <p>Page 28. The People will prefer their Safety to their Paſſions, and their real Security to Forms, when neceſſity calls for Supplies. Had they not been well acquainted with this Principle, they had never ſeen this day of Goſpel-Liberty.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:53659:40"/>
               <head>Cromwell<hi>'s Speech to the Parliament in the Painted Chamber,</hi> Sept. 4. 1654. <hi>hath this remarkable Sentence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>—IT would have been worthy ſuch a meeting as this, to have remembred that which was the riſe, and gave the firſt beginning to all theſe turnings and toſſings that have been upon us: to have given you a Series of the Tranſactions (not of Men but) of the Providence of God, all along unto our late Changes: as alſo the ground of our firſt undertaking to oppoſe that Uſurpation and Tyranny that was upon us in Civils and Spirituals.</p>
               <p>His Speech to the Parliament in the Painted Chamber <hi>Sept.</hi> 12. 1654. ſupplies us with theſe Imitations of the old wheedling Cant.</p>
               <p>—Speaking of the Government he ſays, If God will not bear it up, let it ſink. Then ſpeaking of the Long Parliament, When they were diſſolved (ſays he) there was not ſo much as the barking of a Dog.</p>
               <p>—Poor Men, under this Arbitrary Power, were driven like Flocks of Sheep, by forty in a Morning to the Confiſcation of Goods and Eſtates, without any Man being able to give a reaſon that two of them had deſerved to forfeit a Shilling.</p>
               <p>—So then what was the buſineſs? It was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from a Parliament, that ſhould have been perpetual, to a legiſlative Power always ſitting:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53659:40"/> and the Liberties, Intereſts, and Lives of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not judged by any certain known Laws and Power, but by an Arbitrary Power, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident and neceſſary to Parliaments: to make Mens Eſtates by an Arbitrary Power liable to Confiſcation, and their Perſons to Impriſonments; ſometimes by Laws made after the Fact committed: often by taking the judgment both in Capital and Criminal things to themſelves, who in former times were not known to exerciſe ſuch a Judicature.</p>
               <p>—And as I have appealed to God before you already, I know (and I hope I may ſay it) though it be a tender thing to make Appeals to God; yet in ſuch Exigencies as theſe, I truſt it will not offend His Majeſty: eſpecially to make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Perſons that know God, and know what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is, and what it is to lye before the Lord. I ſay, that as a principal end in calling that Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, was the ſettlement of the Nation, ſo a chief end to my ſelf was, that I might have opportunity to lay down the Power that was in my hands. I ſay it to you again, in the preſence of that God who hath bleſſed and been with me in all my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities and Succeſſes; that was to my ſelf the greateſt end.</p>
               <p>A deſire perhaps (and I am afraid) ſinful enough, to be quit of the Power God had moſt providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially put into my hands, before he called for it, and before thoſe honeſt ends of our fighting were at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and ſetled. I ſay the Authority I had in my hand, being ſo boundleſs as it was, I being by Act of Parliament General of all the Forces in the three Nations of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> (in which unlimited condition I did not deſire to live a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53659:41"/> day) did call that Meeting for the ends before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
               <p>The Preamble to the Proteſtation chargeth the Government with endeavours to ſubvert the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the Exerciſe of an Arbitrary and Tyrannical Government.</p>
               <p>The Petition of the <hi>Londoners</hi> againſt Epiſcopacy, complains, That the ſaid Government is found, by woful Experience, to be a main cauſe and occaſion of many foul Evils, Preſſures, and Grievances of a very high nature unto His Majeſties Subjects, in their Conſciences, Liberties, and Eſtates.</p>
               <p>That Maſter-piece, and Idea of Sedition, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of the State of the Kingdom, extant in <hi>Husband</hi>'s Collections, and elſewhere, hath this vein of Rhetorick running through all the parts of it.</p>
               <p>That Myſtery of Iniquity, and foul Scandal to the Reformation, the ſolemn League and Covenant, expreſſes all along a moſt paſſionate concern for the Liberties of the People.</p>
               <p>The Petition of the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Common-Council of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>Jan.</hi> 41. Which preſſes that the Tower may be put into the hands of Perſons of Truſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> repreſents their great Dangers, Fears, and Diſtractions, upon account of Deſigns driving on, which tend to the utter ruine of the Proteſtant Religion, and of the Lives and Liberties of His Majeſties Loyal Subjects.</p>
               <p>The Petition of the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and the Army to the Houſe of Commons <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. 1649. hath theſe words. Having by our late Labours and Hazards made it appear to the World, at how high a rate we value our juſt Freedom, and God having ſo far
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53659:41"/> owned our Cauſe, as to deliver the Enemies thereof into our hands, we do hold our ſelves bound in mutual duty to each other, to take the beſt care we can for the future, to avoid both the danger of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning into a ſlaviſh Condition, and the chargeable remedy of another War.</p>
               <p>What theſe Wretches meant by their Freedom, Right, Liberty, and Property, they did not fail to explain in a little time: when they uſurped and exerciſed a ſoveraign, unlimited, and abſolute Power over the King himſelf, and all his Subjects: when the Proteſtation was a ſufficient Law, to enforce the bringing in of Money, Plate, and Arms for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Commonwealth: when there were Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances made for Sequeſtring the Eſtates of thoſe who perſiſted in their Loyalty and Duty to the King: when they ſeized the Revenues of the Crown, and the Church: when they raiſed Money without the King's Authority, to carry on a Rebellion againſt him: when they maintained their Army with free Quarter: when they revived a diſtinction declared to be Treaſon by two Acts of Parliament, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between the Kings natural and political Capacity; between his Perſon, and his Power or Authority: when they diſtinguiſhed between the equitable and literal ſenſe of the Law, to give liberty to the Subject, to interpret the King's Laws according to his own pleaſure, and to juſtifie all contempt and diſobedience: when they aſſerted the Legiſlative and Judicative Power to be in the two Houſes of Parliament without the King: laſtly when they declared themſelves to be the irrevocable Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees of the Peoples Lives, Liberties and Properties, without being obliged to give an account of their Truſt.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:53659:42"/>
               <p> What remains, is only the Reader's buſineſs: which is to compare the late Occurrences in this Kingdom with the foregoing Parallels. Whoever does ſo, if he be not blinded by Prejudice, will quickly find, that it is no new thing, for Men to paſs among the Ignorant for great Patriots who have raſed out of their minds all natural ſenſe of Honour and Honeſty; for Vermin, and the Peſts of Humane Society, to ſet up for Heroes, and the Saviours of their Country; and then for the popular Herd to be led away to their Ruine, by the breath of Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the ſmooth faces of Harpies.</p>
               <p>It muſt therefore be needleſs to add any thing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon this Argument, more than the following Conſideration.</p>
               <p>As there are at this day, and have been in former Ages, though in a very ſmall proportion to good Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, Tyrants in many parts of the World, ſo it is at this preſent, as it hath been always heretofore, the hard Fate of the beſt Princes, to be tormented with the Jealouſies of their Subjects: to be charged with the affectation of Tyranny, then conſtantly, when there is the leaſt ground for it: to be always as much miſtruſted by the crazy-headed Rabble while they live, as they are pitied and admired when they are dead.</p>
               <p>Now it is likewiſe the ſame uncharitable corrupt Temper, which renders the People as vexatious to their fellow Subjects, as they are to their Soveraign.</p>
               <p>The number is ſtrangely ſmall of the Men, who have any regard to thoſe Principles of everlaſting Righteouſneſs, which hinder us from tearing and deſtroying one another: of thoſe few that have, and are the wiſeſt, becauſe the beſt of Men, there is not one of many hundreds, who conſiders the miſchief
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53659:42"/> this is done to the World, by the eaſineſs of moſt Perſons, in receiving, and uttering ſcandalous Reports.</p>
               <p>Some People think to make themſelves great, by leſſening or undermining others: but of thoſe that deſign it, there are very few who ſucceed.</p>
               <p>Injuſtice and Calumny are equally pernicious to the World in general, and to the Men that manage by thoſe Arts. For till Integrity and Charity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the univerſal Reſolution of Mankind; till the Experiment comes to be tryed, whether Sincerity, Juſtice, and Benignity, are not better Meaſures than Deceit and Malice, ſurer and readier ways to Proſperity, the World can never be happy: and therefore it is too probable, that it will remain to its Diſſolution, a Maſs of Sin and Miſery.</p>
               <p>The Author's Misfortunes are too little to come into this account. Yet thoſe two reports which were raiſed upon his Preaching the foregoing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ſhould not be quite forgotten. One was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Dreſs, the other about the delivery of his Sermon. As to the former, it is a matter of Diſpute between Perſons of different Years and Tempers, who can never agree upon the Point of Decency in Attire. But what it is to read a Sermon, both young and old, the Candid and the Moroſe, the Spightful and the Kind, do all agree in their Verdict, however they are divided in the other Caſe.</p>
               <p>Now, whenas the preceding Sermon, which was ſpoken as readily without Book, as any thing perhaps, that hath been delivered before His Majeſty (which is well enough remembred at the Court) was ſaid to be read word for word, and that report, as falſe as it was, divulged and credited in all parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, it ſupplies us with the following Concluſion.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53659:43"/>
               <p> If a private Perſon may at any time be brought upon the Stage, and expoſed to the cenſure of the World, by Men as little as himſelf; it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Government ſhould be ſuſpected and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered, when great, united, ſubtle Factions, make it their buſineſs to miſrepreſent it: when its Friends are modeſt, ſlow, unactive, and ſecure: when its Enemies are bold, reſtleſs, and implacable: when the People are diſtruſtful, fickle, conceited, petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and <hi>mutinous, to that degree of madneſs,</hi> that if the Devil of Sedition goes out of them for a while, and the unclean Spirit walks through the dry places that were lately covered with Blood, and a torrent of Miſeries, he can find no reſt, till he returns to his <hi>Houſe from whence he came out:</hi> that <hi>Houſe,</hi> where he roars out his pretended Fears of Superſtition and Slavery, in thoſe hideous yells which fright the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People out of their Wits. When he cometh to the <hi>Houſe,</hi> he findeth it empty, and ſwept, and garniſhed too with the faireſt Pretences for Religion, Law, Right, Liberty, and Property. Then goeth he, and taketh to him ſeven other Apoſtate Spirits, a ſelect number of corrupt and diſgraced Miniſters of State: they enter into the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and dwell there; and the laſt State of that miſerable poſſeſſed People, is worſe than the firſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> part. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>r.</hi> Arias Montanus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53659:43"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
